In this video we will learn about reference. Reference feature is available only in C++.
This is not a part of C language.So, let us understand reference. A reference is a nickname given to a
variable or alias given to a variable.
Let me write and show you.
Suppose this is a function, so I am using a main ( ) function, main ( )
Suppose already I have a variable some name a and it is having value 10.
So, how it looks like inside the main memory is
This is the main function, inside the code section, and inside its stack frame there is a variable having
value name a and with value 10.
Suppose there is some code in main ( ) function.
Now inside this I want to have a reference to that variable a.
So the method of declaring reference is
int r ; r is a reference.
You can use any name, I'm using r. Then how to make it as a reference? write &
& just before the variable name. See, if nothing is there before the variable name,
it is a data variable, if there is a * before the variable name,
it's a pointer, and if & is before the variable name,
It's a reference. Now, this reference must be initialized when declared.
This is the declaration and assigned with a. So, this is initialized with a.
So what does it mean when you have a reference that is referring to a?
This means, this a itself is called as r.
So, that same is having one more name r. So you can call this value with name a as well as with r.
So now you have 2 names for the same value inside the memory.
So it means, if that variable a is occupying 2 bytes of memory, let's say 200 is the address and 201,
2 bytes and value 10.
Now what is the address of a? 200.
What is the address of r? That is also 200.
So, it means, if I print using cout<<a; I'll get the value 10, and if I say, r++, then this
means this value is increased to 11 because the same value is r now.
So, address of r is also 200.
If I say cout<<r; then it will print value 11. So, the same value if I again say cout<<a; then I'll get
the same value.
11. So a reference is nothing but another name to a variable.
Now the question is, Why do you need another name to the same variable? when you already have the name
a, why do you want another name r?
So basically, this is useful in parameter passing, and
this is a very useful feature of C++; for writing small functions,
we use references instead of using pointers. So when we learn about the parameter passing, that time I
will explain you what is the usage of reference. Right now,
In my example program this is a simple main function, in this, I don't need any reference, because already
I have 'a', I can use 'a'. But, for explanation I have used a simple code what a reference means, Reference is
nothing but another name given to a variable.
So the actual name is a and this is alias,
So 'r' is just another name of 'a'. Now, that's it about reference.
So what is reference,
How to declare it and how to initialize it,
I have explained.
Now, what is the actual purpose of reference?
We will see that in coming videos, where I will talk about functions and parameter passing.
So, that's all in this video.